Have you ever believed
in something like so
much and then just
suddenly started to question
those beliefs? Well, recently,
when I was repositioning
my channel from the
YouTube growth guy to
the get sales views
and leads from YouTube
guy, I told myself,
this new audience, it
doesn't want metaphors in
content. It just wants
instructions. So I started
testing out content that
basically went against all
of the things that
I'd always believed in.
And after testing this
for a while, I
looked at my RevTrack
data that shows me
what's generating sales. And
I noticed four to
five videos that had
made the most money
all had one thing
in common. I'd use
metaphors in the emotion
brick to help make
the information feel new,
easy, and inspiring. And
it worked. So in
this video, I'm gonna
show you how to
know when to use
a metaphor, how to
plan one without overcomplicating
it, how to avoid
the common mistakes that
kill them, and more
importantly, how to use
them to increase retention,
trust, and conversions. So
to start, let's just
answer the question you
probably have, what even
is a metaphor? Well,
a metaphor is a
quick comparison that swaps
a complex idea for
a vivid, familiar image
so viewers grasp the
point in an instant.
Here's an example. So
here we have two
different channels and the
amount of jelly beans
in each class represents
their following size. So
channel one here spent
five years building theirs
and they can just
about afford to go
full -time and hire
some help. Yay. Channel
two, however, spent a
year building theirs. It's
not very big, but
they're on the cusp
of quitting their job
and are already paying
an editor to free
up their time. Now,
this is the crazy
part. In a year,
channel two will be
making 10 times more
than channel one as
a result of this.
But why? Well, let's
just say both of
these guys are in
the same niche, the
self -help niche. It's
a very big one.
Channel one went out
looking to build the
biggest audience they possibly
could. So what they
did was make videos
that appealed to as
many people as they
could by covering a
lot of different topics.
So one video was
about productivity and the
next was about why
you're not happy in
life and the next
was about getting out
of a rut. All
in the chase of
monster views. Channel two,
on the other hand,
asked themselves, who can
I serve better than
anyone else with my
skillset and experience? And
then who wants this
type of content? And
then they only focused
on that. What that
meant was they only
made videos to help
people overcome, let's say,
being more productive by
creating simple systems in
their life and that's
it. But how does
that make channel two
more money though? But
why is that so
powerful? Well, firstly, it's
because they take something
abstract or technical or
overwhelming and make it
feel simple, relatable and
easy to understand. They
basically give, they give
a viewer clarity. So
they go, oh, it's
like that. Got it.
Secondly, when your content's
filled with facts and
instructions, only 10 %
gets remembered. When you
wrap a lesson in
a strong visual metaphor,
65 % can remain
up here. And then
thirdly, a good metaphor
doesn't just explain something.
It makes you feel
something and it triggers
that emotional reaction. And
that's what turns passive
viewers into fans. Fourthly,
it massively, massively differentiates
you. Most creators are
lazy and they cannot
be bothered with the
emotion, the rhetoric at
all. And because metaphors
are very hard to
come up with, this,
if you nail it,
will make you look
like someone who cares
and goes further, which
reflects onto your business
too. Now, metaphors take
a lot of time
to come up with
and they're much harder
to write than stories
or visual demos. But
when you get it
right, your Stripe account's
gonna go ping. Okay,
so now you know
why they work. I
need you to avoid
the biggest trap my
clients get into when
they've done my program.
And that is they
try and shoehorn metaphors
into every video they
make because they say,
I just want to
use metaphors. It doesn't
work like that. A
metaphor is a tool
for a specific job.
So the first question
you need to ask
is, should I even
use a metaphor in
this part to make
my point? So here's
a simple filter to
help you decide when
to use them or
if you should even
use them. So if
the concept you're trying
to teach is abstract
or technical or very
hard to picture, a
metaphor can make it
tangible. If you ask
yourself, have I explained
this idea before, but
people still don't get
it, a metaphor can
help it click. If
you ask, is this
part of the video
dry or data heavy
or low on emotion,
a metaphor can spark
interest and make things
feel new and fresh.
If you ask, do
I want the viewers
to remember this without
taking notes, you want
to use a metaphor.
If you say no
to all of those,
don't make a metaphor,
just use a story
or a visual memo,
but also don't use
a metaphor when the
idea is already really
clear on its own.
Also don't use a
metaphor when you've already
used a metaphor in
the exact same emotion
brick. The whole idea
is, you say it
once, the viewers get
it, and then want
the logic. So just
keep them very simple
to start. You also
need to realize that
a good metaphor shouldn't
take minutes to explain
and have tons of
moving parts. They need
to simplify things, not
bolt on complexity. So
if your metaphor sounds
like a journal entry
or a riddle, your
viewers are gonna be
like, this person's weird
and they're gone. Also
don't over -explain them.
So if you turn
around and go, just
to clarify, this box
is the thumbnail
because it's something they
need to open.
There's no point in
a metaphor if you
explain it. So just
say it and move
on. And if it
doesn't land on its
own, it's not the
right metaphor. And finally,
if you're sitting there
going, how do I
come up with something
clever here? And you're
really struggling, don't. A
good metaphor should come
quickly. If it's taking
like half an hour,
an hour to plan
one, it's gonna feel
awkward and forced, don't
use it. Just go
back to a story
or a visual demo.
Okay, so those are
the traps. Now what
I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna show you
how to build a
metaphor from scratch. So
step one, you just
define the problem. You
start by asking what's
the confusing, dry, or
abstract thing that I
want people to help
understand. For example, people
treat a first date
like a guarantee and
get crushed when it
doesn't lead to a
second one. Step two,
you then just define
the solution. So think
about what you're trying
to get the viewers
to do. So the
example might be like,
slow down, don't over
-invest, collect clues before
committing, and read the
signals better. Step three,
you then find like
a relatable comparison. Now
basically you're looking for
something familiar that works
in the same way.
So in this case,
what we could do
is we could compare
it to wine tasting.
So you might say
something like, you take
a sip, you swell,
you smell, you don't
chug the bottle and
assume it's perfect for
you and yours to
keep forever. That's kind
of it. So basically
when you're planning, you're
just looking for what's
something that you understand
already that works like
the point I'm trying
to make. And that's
kind of it. And
then after your metaphor,
when you've used it
in the emotion brick,
we need to bring
back those cheeky little
transitions so that we
can then connect it
to the logic brick.
Otherwise people are gonna
go, why on earth
has he just, told
me about a Louis
Vuitton box? What's that
got to do with
anything? So remember the
goal of a transition
is to help the
viewer go from, that's
a clever metaphor to,
okay, now tell me
how to do this
thing. In a way
that hooks them, lets
them know the video
is moving forward and
helps them understand why
the following information matters
to them without ever
saying, let me show
this why this matters
to you. So here's
some post metaphor transitions
that are pretty much
exactly the same as
the ones that you
can use on visual
demos and stories. So
for example, so what
does that actually mean
for you? Or let
me show you how
that applies in real
life, or here's how
to fix that step
by step. All right,
so that's metaphors, but
here's the final thing
I want you to
leave with. This takes
a huge amount of
practice. Even if you
get the structure, it
doesn't mean the metaphor
is always just gonna
pop into your head
first try. Sometimes it
will, sometimes it won't.
This is another skill
to develop in your
whole transformation. It's a
painful one and you're
gonna get better the
more you try. So
now we know the
tools that we can
use and practice over
a long time and
not be instantly good
at in the emotion
brick. Moving on to
the next video where
I'm gonna start teaching
you how to use
the logic brick. Exciting.